<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Exploring Machine Learning Optimizatios for Pair Selection in Pairs Trading</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Exploring Machine Learning Optimizatios for Pair Selection in Pairs Trading</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ausarbeitung</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/docs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/docs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Pairstrading ist eine nichtdirektionale Handelsstrategie, die unabhängig von der Marktrichtung funktioniert &lt;a href=&#34;#ref-Vidyamurthy%202004&#34; id=&#34;cite-Vidyamurthy 2004&#34;&gt;(Vidyamurthy 2004, p. 8)&lt;/a&gt;. Sie basiert auf historischen Zusammenhängen zwischen zwei Wertpapieren (Zeitreihen) $X_i(t)$ und $X_j(t)$ und nutzt temporäre Abweichungen in deren Preisbeziehung zur Gewinnerzielung aus. Im verbreiteten, statistischen Pairstrading werden zwei Hauptansätze unterschieden: kointegrationsbasierte und korrelationsbasierte Verfahren. &lt;a href=&#34;#ref-Engle%201987&#34; id=&#34;cite-Engle 1987&#34;&gt;Engle et al. 1987&lt;/a&gt; legten die theoretischen Grundlagen der Kointegration, &lt;a href=&#34;#ref-Vidyamurthy%202004&#34; id=&#34;cite-Vidyamurthy 2004&#34;&gt;Vidyamurthy et al. 2004&lt;/a&gt; entwickelten deren Anwendung im Pairstrading, und &lt;a href=&#34;#ref-Gatev%202006&#34; id=&#34;cite-Gatev 2006&#34;&gt;Gatev et al. 2006&lt;/a&gt; etablierten den korrelationsbasierten Ansatz. Pairstrading umfasst zwei fundamentale Schritte: das Identifizieren geeigneter Paare und deren Handel.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Backtester</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/backtester/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/backtester/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;configuration-sidebar&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Configuration Sidebar&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#configuration-sidebar&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Configuration Sidebar serves as the central control panel for the backtesting application. All analyses rely on these settings.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;window&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/gif/config.gif&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;market--strategy&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Market &amp;amp; Strategy&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#market--strategy&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first step involves selecting a market from the &lt;code&gt;Select Market&lt;/code&gt; dropdown. This choice determines which stocks and strategies become available. After market selection, the &lt;code&gt;Select Strategy&lt;/code&gt; dropdown displays only compatible strategies. Without a valid selection, the application shows &amp;ldquo;No strategies available for selected market&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Backtesting Demonstrator Setup Guide</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/setup/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The microservices architecture demonstrates a complete backtesting pipeline for pairs trading strategies. Each service fulfills a specific role in the data processing and analysis workflow.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/archi.drawio.png&#34; width=&#34;800&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Notebook Runner&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;code&gt;notebook_runner&lt;/code&gt;) service leverages papermill to execute all possible permutations of pair-finding algorithms and trading strategies through parameterized Jupyter notebooks. This allows for systematic generation and testing of different strategy combinations across various market conditions. The &lt;strong&gt;MinIO&lt;/strong&gt; blob storage service serves as the central data repository, containing both the theoretical results presented in the research and raw market data. Additionally, all newly generated strategy runs are automatically stored here, creating a comprehensive historical record of backtesting results. The &lt;strong&gt;Analytics&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;code&gt;analytics&lt;/code&gt;) service processes trade data from the blob storage along with raw market data to calculate comprehensive performance metrics. This backend service handles all computational-heavy operations including risk metrics, return calculations, and portfolio statistics. The &lt;strong&gt;Streamlit&lt;/strong&gt; application provides a unified interface for data visualization, performance analysis, and strategy management. Users can explore raw data, examine trading results, analyze performance metrics, and commission new notebook runs directly through the web interface. All services are located under &lt;code&gt;src/backtester/services/&lt;/code&gt; and communicate through REST APIs and shared storage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Results</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/results/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/results/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Die nachfolgende Auswertung der Ergebnisse Hypothese: &lt;em&gt;Machine Learning-basierte Ansätze zur Paaridentifikation übertreffen traditionelle kointegrationsbasierte Verfahren im Pairs Trading.&lt;/em&gt; Die durch Machine Learning Ansätze gefundenen Paare schlagen im Gegensatz zu den kointegrationsbasierten Verfahren mit ihren jeweiligen Strategien den Markt ($F_{100}$: +7,9%, $N_{100}$: +15,8% für das Jahr 2024).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;performance-am-n_100-index&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Performance am $N_{100}$-Index&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#performance-am-n_100-index&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Am $N_{100}$ erreichte der Gradient Boost Regressor 20,90% Jahresrendite (Z-Score) bei einer Sharpe Ratio von 6,16. Dies entspricht einer Marktoutperformance von 5,1 Prozentpunkten gegenüber dem $N_{100}$ Index. Der Affinity Propagation Ansatz erzielte 17,98% mit einer Sharpe Ratio von 7,48. Die traditionellen Kointegrationsansätze erreichten dagegen -1,13% oder wiesen zweistellige Verluste auf.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
