<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Exploring Machine Learning Optimizatios for Pair Selection in Pairs Trading</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Exploring Machine Learning Optimizatios for Pair Selection in Pairs Trading</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ausarbeitung</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/docs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/docs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Pairstrading ist eine nichtdirektionale Handelsstrategie, die unabh채ngig von der Marktrichtung funktioniert &lt;a href=&#34;#ref-Vidyamurthy%202004&#34; id=&#34;cite-Vidyamurthy 2004&#34;&gt;(Vidyamurthy 2004, p. 8)&lt;/a&gt;. Sie basiert auf historischen Zusammenh채ngen zwischen zwei Wertpapieren (Zeitreihen) $X_i(t)$ und $X_j(t)$ und nutzt tempor채re Abweichungen in deren Preisbeziehung zur Gewinnerzielung aus. Im verbreiteten, statistischen Pairstrading werden zwei Hauptans채tze unterschieden: kointegrationsbasierte und korrelationsbasierte Verfahren. &lt;a href=&#34;#ref-Engle%201987&#34; id=&#34;cite-Engle 1987&#34;&gt;Engle et al. 1987&lt;/a&gt; legten die theoretischen Grundlagen der Kointegration, &lt;a href=&#34;#ref-Vidyamurthy%202004&#34; id=&#34;cite-Vidyamurthy 2004&#34;&gt;Vidyamurthy et al. 2004&lt;/a&gt; entwickelten deren Anwendung im Pairstrading, und &lt;a href=&#34;#ref-Gatev%202006&#34; id=&#34;cite-Gatev 2006&#34;&gt;Gatev et al. 2006&lt;/a&gt; etablierten den korrelationsbasierten Ansatz. Pairstrading umfasst zwei fundamentale Schritte: das Identifizieren geeigneter Paare und deren Handel.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Backtesting Demonstrator Setup Guide</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/setup/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The microservices architecture demonstrates a complete backtesting pipeline for pairs trading strategies. Each service fulfills a specific role in the data processing and analysis workflow.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/archi.drawio.png&#34; width=&#34;800&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Notebook Runner&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;code&gt;notebook_runner&lt;/code&gt;) service leverages papermill to execute all possible permutations of pair-finding algorithms and trading strategies through parameterized Jupyter notebooks. This allows for systematic generation and testing of different strategy combinations across various market conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;MinIO&lt;/strong&gt; blob storage service serves as the central data repository, containing both the theoretical results presented in the research and raw market data. Additionally, all newly generated strategy runs are automatically stored here, creating a comprehensive historical record of backtesting results.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
